<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>emacs on Frame Perfect</title>
    <link>https://wneville.com/tags/emacs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in emacs on Frame Perfect</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://wneville.com/tags/emacs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My Ongoing Journey with Emacs</title>
      <link>https://wneville.com/blog/my-emacs-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wneville.com/blog/my-emacs-journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;init&#34;&gt;init&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m rapidly becoming known as &amp;ldquo;that Emacs guy&amp;rdquo; in my office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very vocal about my love for this ~35 year old piece of software, and (unsuccessfully) evangelize it amongst my peers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever one of my coworkers shows the smallest amount of interest in it, such as &amp;ldquo;Hey that presentation you gave with the code blocks, what was that in?&amp;rdquo;, it&amp;rsquo;s off to the races.
I&amp;rsquo;m prone to inundate them with additional reading materials and youtube videos about emacs and org-mode and why they should also consider using it to organize their life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I&amp;rsquo;m rarely asked about it twice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still consider myself to be very junior as an Emacs user. There&amp;rsquo;s much I do not know, and even more that I do not know that I do not know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, I&amp;rsquo;ve been casually interested in Emacs for about two years, and have been a fervent user with it as my primary IDE and organization tool for the past six-eight months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this post, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to detail out my ever ongoing journey as an Emacs user. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that this will prove to be useful to newcomers to Emacs, or that it will at least expand my currently very
small social network of Emacs users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;history&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-dark-ages&#34;&gt;the dark ages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s get one thing out of the way - while pursuing my computer science degree in college, I was mostly a Vim user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t really a power user, but I could navigate effectively.
My Vim config was mostly copied from others on the internet, but without understanding what everything did.
Once I graduated college and took a non-coding job, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really have much text editing work to do, and I dropped off Vim.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vim is still my go-to when remoting into servers and making quick changes, which honestly is the perfect use case for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;pursuing-enlightenment&#34;&gt;pursuing enlightenment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emacs has been on my radar ever since I started getting into programming, but my first attempt at using it was probably in 2015.
I was working as a technician at an IT helpdesk, so I wasn&amp;rsquo;t very opinionated about my text editors yet.
A friend of mine was working at a startup doing Android work, and his boss at the time used Emacs keybindings in IntelliJ.
Apparently whenever his boss came over and wanted to type something, he would fail due to the built in IntelliJ bindings, so he &amp;ldquo;strongly encouraged&amp;rdquo; my friend to switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After hearing about the interesting keybindings, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d go straight to the source: I downloaded Emacs to see what it was all about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I probably lasted less than 5 minutes. It seemed so old school! The splash screen was ugly, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what all the UI elements were, and I struggled through the built in tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I promptly uninstalled Emacs, and moved on with my life, proclaiming that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I switched jobs to an Ad Tech company doing Tier 1.5 work (vendor certification work), and during this time I mostly used Notepad++ for jamming down random notes.
I never saved any of them, so I probably ended that job with 300 tabs in NP++ memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reattempting-enlightenment&#34;&gt;reattempting enlightenment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early 2017, I got myself my first real programming job - huzzah!
The role was in the IT sector of a bank, and I was working on a platform that exposed APIs for working with in-house infrastructure.
This was a greenfield project, and we decided to build it with a container and microservice-first approach.
Being a large enterprise financial company, we settled on the JVM as our application runtime, with Java as the core language.
Naturally, IntelliJ was the IDE of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t long until I discovered Clojure.
Clojure is a functional programming language - a lisp that runs in the JVM. It&amp;rsquo;s elegant and production ready.
To this day, I&amp;rsquo;ve not had the opportunity to work with Clojure much, but I&amp;rsquo;ve always been in love with its principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided I wanted to learn Clojure, and to try to integrate it into our API platform - if all our microservices were JVM based, who says one couldn&amp;rsquo;t be in Clojure?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I borrowed the book &lt;strong&gt;Clojure for the Brave and True&lt;/strong&gt; from my team lead at the time, who also had pipe dreams of using Clojure for a financial modeling startup.
Brave Clojure (as I&amp;rsquo;ll call it henceforth) is a great book - it has hearty doses of humor, and is a must read if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in Clojure.
At the end of the first chapter, the book describes a few different popular IDE options for Clojure - namely, Emacs as well as IntelliJ with the Cursive plugin.
However, the author is moderatly opinionated, and the second chapter of the book is entirely about configuring and using Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pored over every word in this Emacs chapter - I found it fascinating.
It was describing a way to configure and use Emacs to achieve a productive programming workflow.
This is what was lacking on my first Emacs attempt, I had no goal - I tried using Emacs for the sake of using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter does have one issue though, which is that the author provides a zip file of a recommended Emacs configuration.
This configuration has not aged entirely well (there have been a few packages in the last few years which would clean it up, such as &lt;em&gt;use-package&lt;/em&gt;), and will not suit all users.
Additionally, if it ever breaks, the user will likely be dead in the water on what to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I used this configuration and followed every step of the chapter. I also gave the built in tutorial another go, to greater success.
I was beginning to understand the fluidity of using Emacs, but I still had no knowledge in configuring and tweaking it for my use cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now felt comfortable with Emacs, but pretty much only for Clojure with the Brave Clojure configuration.
It felt a bit like having one highly specialized tool in your work belt that you used once a year, if ever.
I ended up not having too much spare time to work on Clojure, and as a result my Emacs usage dwindled into nothingness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did persist however, were the keybindings.
I made the decision to swap my IntelliJ keybindings to be the built in Emacs keymap.
It did a pretty good job mapping navigational keys and common operations to their default Emacs values.
Quickly, nobody besides me could use my IntelliJ anymore (made more difficult with my keyboard, a HHKB), and I had the muscle memory for navigational keys well developed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enlightenment-as-a-primary-ide&#34;&gt;enlightenment as a primary IDE&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the beginning of 2019, and I&amp;rsquo;ve got another new job - my first with an actual &lt;em&gt;software engineer&lt;/em&gt; title.
We now jump to present tense, as this is my current job as of this writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tech stack at this role is Python on the backend.
I&amp;rsquo;d hardly worked with Python prior to this role, so in my first month I watched some professional development videos to get up to speed on the language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it came time to choose an IDE, I originally settled with PyCharm.
It was almost identical to IntelliJ with which I was already familiar, and most of my coworkers were also using PyCharm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the next few months, a few catalyzing factors lead to me using Emacs exclusively, which we&amp;rsquo;ll go over in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;community&#34;&gt;Community&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I&amp;rsquo;m the only person at my current role who uses Emacs, I started to meet others who did use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started showing up a little more regularly to the Emacs NY Meetup, and chatting with other there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started watching more YouTube videos about Emacs topics, which were mostly recorded from previous sessions of the NY meetup which I had begun attending.
This spurred my interest in some other topics, which I will discuss below, but mainly the videos helped instill that sense of community further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started listening to all the Emacs related podcasts that were available, getting a much better understanding of the ecosystem in the process.
Emacs is a lot less intimidating when you understand to what names like &lt;em&gt;helm&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;company&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;projectile&lt;/em&gt; pertain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly and most importantly, I discovered my friend Adrien is a pseudo-celebrity in the Emacs community.
He&amp;rsquo;s distributed packages for managing Kubernetes, Habitica and Todoist from inside Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;org-mode&#34;&gt;Org-Mode&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure if the the population of new Emacs users from the past ~15 years was surveyed on what made them try Emacs, I&amp;rsquo;m sure Org-Mode would feature prominently as a reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Org-Mode is extremely feature rich and difficult to explain succinctly, but at a high level it is an Emacs major mode that is well suited to note taking, task tracking and outlining.
Many users manage all aspects of their productive life via org-mode.
One of the coolest aspects of org-mode is the agenda view, which will consolidate your TODOs and calendar events striped across multiple org files and present them in a daily/weekly view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I discovered org-mode, I was staggered across 3 different apps to manage my work to-do&amp;rsquo;s, personal to-do&amp;rsquo;s, list management, Dungeons and Dragons organization, etc.
Org-mode was clearly the tool that I wanted and needed, and this pushed me heavily into the full-time Emacs camp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As of this writing, I use org-mode primarily for note taking as well as managing personal project coding TODOs. I use an external todo app (Todoist) for all other things. Once I have time to spend on it, I can configure the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/abrochard/emacs-todoist&#34;&gt;package&lt;/a&gt; Adrien wrote to get some Emacs Todoist integration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&#34;experience&#34;&gt;Experience&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I was just in a better position to dive into Emacs at this junction.
I had gotten more experience wrangling configurations, reading documentation and writing code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t believe that you need to be a programmer (or otherwise highly technical) to use Emacs effectively.
That being said, I believe that the experience I gathered in my professional career helped me develop a tinkerer&amp;rsquo;s passion.
Having this passion fuels my need to endlessly tinker and tweak my Emacs setup, the results of which bring me a lot of joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lets-get-technical-what-packages-were-critical-to-using-emacs-as-the-primary-ide&#34;&gt;let&amp;rsquo;s get technical: what packages were critical to using Emacs as the primary IDE?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this section, I use the term &amp;ldquo;productivity&amp;rdquo; to refer to my ability to and the ease with which I am able to translate thought into code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I was willing to commit to Emacs as my primary IDE, I had to ensure that I could at least be close to as productive as I was in my existing tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first tool that I really needed to do my job in Emacs was a python mode. I settled on &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/jorgenschaefer/elpy&#34;&gt;elpy&lt;/a&gt;, as this seemed a common choice.
Elpy offered the IDE-like experience I needed for Python development. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite as feature rich as PyCharm with regards to flexible code navigation and global refactoring (Note: JetBrains global refactoring is black magic), but it certainly helped me get up and running. Elpy also helped me to learn more about the ecosystem - I learned about packages like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/company-mode/company-mode&#34;&gt;company&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/flycheck/flycheck&#34;&gt;flycheck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I was up and running with a Python IDE. However, I was &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; clunky at navigating around Emacs and my project; I could not switch buffers effectively, and I would consistently find files by exact path (watching me do this was a nightmare, trust me). The next two packages that I really needed were &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/emacs-helm/helm&#34;&gt;Helm&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/bbatsov/projectile&#34;&gt;Projectile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helm is an incremental search and selection narrowing framework, but it feels like a lot more than that. In the way that I use it, Helm is effectively a tool that, when searching, opens new buffers with results that are easily navigable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projectile is a tool that makes it easy to work with &amp;ldquo;projects&amp;rdquo;. In my context, a project is almost always a git repository. Projectile offers functions to quickly switch between registered projects, find files within a project, find text patterns within a project, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I&amp;rsquo;m almost caught up to my original productivity, with the added benefit that I was having a lot of fun as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of curiosity, I swapped over from elpy to using &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/emacs-lsp/lsp-mode&#34;&gt;lsp-mode&lt;/a&gt;. Once I got it configured, I found it to be snappier and got me closer to that &amp;ldquo;IDE&amp;rdquo; feeling with features like peeking into definitions of functions. I&amp;rsquo;m still at the time of this writing running into occasional issues with lsp-mode - it&amp;rsquo;s pretty bleeding edge at this point, especially if you&amp;rsquo;re using the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/palantir/python-language-server&#34;&gt;pyls&lt;/a&gt;. Some of my issues will be resolved with my primary work codebase completes its python2 -&amp;gt; python3 migration, with the eventual dependency bump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another package that I started leveraging at this point was &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/joaotavora/yasnippet&#34;&gt;yasnippet&lt;/a&gt;. This is a legendary package - it&amp;rsquo;s a snippet creator, but it allows embedding arbitrary emacs-lisp code into your templates, so it becomes something much more powerful. I&amp;rsquo;ve still only scratched the surface here. I highly recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/AndreaCrotti/yasnippet-snippets&#34;&gt;this community library&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package that has consistently had my coworkers ooh-ing and aah-ing is &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pashky/restclient.el&#34;&gt;restclient&lt;/a&gt;. This makes making HTTP requests &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; smooth, and has allowed me to almost entirely offboard from Postman.
Additionally, my friend Adrien is working on a package, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/abrochard/walkman&#34;&gt;walkman&lt;/a&gt;, to do HTTP requests in an org file. With a little more customization, one can get an even more Postman-like experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still have a ways to go - I still don&amp;rsquo;t have great tools for refactoring, nor have I spent much time sharpening the knife of making my editing more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;in-summary&#34;&gt;in summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that this was an interesting read for you, and that it maybe sparks an interest in using Emacs yourself - as well as being an efficient tool, it can be a fun hobby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel encouraged to reach out to me on any/all social platforms to chat about Emacs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
