<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>self-improvement on Frame Perfect</title>
    <link>https://wneville.com/tags/self-improvement/</link>
    <description>Recent content in self-improvement on Frame Perfect</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 18:03:29 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://wneville.com/tags/self-improvement/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fostering a Healthier Relationship with Digital Media Consumption and the Ever-Present Smartphone</title>
      <link>https://wneville.com/blog/healthier-digital-media-and-smartphone-consumption/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 18:03:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://wneville.com/blog/healthier-digital-media-and-smartphone-consumption/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-1&#34;&gt;
The Trouble with Time
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-1&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Big shocker, I know; me and nearly everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, if you were to ask me how much time I spend on my phone each day on average, I don&amp;#39;t think I&amp;#39;d be able to give you even an approximation.
Somewhere between 1 and 5 hours?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With the addition of the &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Screen Time&lt;/code&gt; in iOS, I now have access to a report of exactly how much time I spend on my phone, with that time broken apart on a per-app basis.
&lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Screen Time&lt;/code&gt; has been in iOS for a while, but I&amp;#39;ve never really bothered to check it or to configure any time limits on apps.
Maybe I&amp;#39;m scared of quantifying the time I&amp;#39;ve spent on my phone, especially on apps for services such as Reddit, Twitter and Discord.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Honestly though, that&amp;#39;s all just a big sunk cost fallacy.
It doesn&amp;#39;t really matter how much time I have spent historically on my phone, because that&amp;#39;s time that has already been spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What does matter is being more intentional with how I&amp;#39;m spending my time, and spending less time on my phone if that&amp;#39;s not where I want to be spending said time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Forgive me for being morbid, but a big value in my life is the following statement: &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Time is a limited resource of which I do not know the quantity.&lt;/code&gt;
Eventually I will run out of time, and I do not know when that will be.
Therefore, I want to be as &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;intentional as possible&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in how I spend my time; the ultimate goal of this is to live what I consider to be a fulfilling and meaningful life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-2&#34;&gt;
What do I want to do with my time, and why?
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-2&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve identified that I&amp;#39;m spending what I feel to be &amp;#34;too much&amp;#34; time on pursuits I view to not be worth the time spent; this is mostly excess time on my phone, which we&amp;#39;ll analyze further in a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What pursuits or activities are &amp;#34;worth the time&amp;#34;? This is a difficult question to answer (at least for me it is), and the answer to this question is entirely subjective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I could identify the set of activities that I deem worthy of my time, and schedule out all available time in my calendar to ensure I&amp;#39;m consistently spending time on worthwhile things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, following a schedule of what I had deduced to be the optimal &amp;#34;life&amp;#34;…that doesn&amp;#39;t sound like the life I want to live.
Additionally, what I view to be important to me will certainly change over time, especially after major life events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As a result, I feel that identifying what my core &lt;em&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; are is a better way to approach this exercise.
Whenever I go to engage in an activity, I can briefly reflect on whether that activity is aligned or otherwise contributes to my values, and thus proceed accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While my values may mutate over time, they are core principles to me and should remain fairly static.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-3&#34;&gt;
Values
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-3&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-4&#34;&gt;
Loved Ones
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-4&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sartre&amp;#39;s Hell may be &amp;#34;other people&amp;#34;, but I want my paradise to be spending time with my loved ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Honestly, I have been distracted away from this value to the point where writing the previous statement felt dishonest; it&amp;#39;s critical to my longterm happiness that I make time with my loved ones my top priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Activities that embody this value&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spending &amp;#34;active&amp;#34; time with friends/family, whether in person or over a video call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-5&#34;&gt;
Continuous Self-Improvement
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-5&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love to learn new things and commit to pursuits that demonstrate measurable self improvement to a fault; I am especially susceptible to skill intensive games.
I will throw myself deeply into a new game, spend hours upon hours learning as much as I can…only to get distracted by and commit to a new game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I recognize that I have this drive for self improvement, as misplaced as it often can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Ideally, I want to commit to pursuits where I am learning or growing as a person; results of these pursuits ideally benefit my personal or professional life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Activities that embody this value&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exercise&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading (Non-Fiction)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Language Learning (Chinese)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;headline-6&#34;&gt;
Foster Creativity and Create
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-6&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to the value of &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Continuous Self-Improvement&lt;/code&gt;, I want to ensure that I&amp;#39;m fostering my own creativity and creating things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
When I was a teenager, I was very much into poetry - it helped me to express myself in areas where I felt uncomfortable confiding in others.
I haven&amp;#39;t written poetry in quite a while, and while I wouldn&amp;#39;t restrict myself from picking that back up one day, I think it&amp;#39;s more important that I foster my general creativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These days I tend to express myself more through coding, and while that doesn&amp;#39;t express my emotions to the same extent that poetry does, it&amp;#39;s a pursuit that allows me to create something from an idea and thus gives me a sense of satisfaction.
I also express myself and introspect by way of this blog; any pursuits that influence me to keep writing are ones that I would consider valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
On this front, consuming content created by others (especially digital content) can be a way of fostering my own creativity.
I am not restricting myself from this, but this is approaching the area where careful balance is required; I must very intentionally choose the movies, tv shows, online videos, podcasts, etc. that I wish to consume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Activities that embody this value&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading (Fiction, Non-Fiction, Blogs, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Programming&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consuming Intentionally Chosen Digital Media (Movies, TV Shows, Podcasts, Games, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-7&#34;&gt;
Content Troughs and &amp;#34;Infinite&amp;#34; Media
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-7&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forgive me for the introspection of the previous section; while valuable for crafting my own guiding light, we have diverged a bit from the original intent of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Reflecting on my values before engaging in an activity and proceeding accordingly is great and all, but I don&amp;#39;t believe that this solves the original issue of &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;spending too much time on my phone&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Pulling my phone out of my pocket is a physical habit - I have years of muscle memory built up of reaching for the device whenever I am not actively engaged in an activity.
Even worse is when I pull out my phone when I &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;am&lt;/span&gt; engaged in an activity such as programming or talking to someone. At best this is a distraction, at worst it&amp;#39;s downright disrespectful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Even over the course of the days where I have been working on this blog post, with the intent to reduce my phone time on my mind, I still find myself scrolling ad nauseam.
When I wake up, the first thing I do is reach for my phone and find myself scrolling through Twitter, Instagram, Reddit and Discord before I even wake up fully.
Sometimes I&amp;#39;ll stay in the bed for a full 30 extra minutes before getting started with my day; I could be having a coffee and enjoying the cool morning breeze out on the roof instead!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can feel myself driven by a sense of FOMO, or &amp;#34;Fear Of Missing Out&amp;#34;; a sense of wanting to catch up on everything that might have happened while I was asleep drives me to spend this time each morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The content that instills this feeling is what I&amp;#39;m going to describe as a &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;content trough&lt;/code&gt;.
I do not use this term to liken all the content to that of livestock feed - much of this content is entertaining and worthwhile.
Some content creators put a lot of hard work into their content creation and I greatly respect their efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Content troughs are carefully designed to keep you looking at it; this makes sense, they often make more profit the longer they keep you looking.
They do this by using algorithms that determine what to show you next based on your previous viewing habits.
These algorithms are &lt;em&gt;pretty damn good&lt;/em&gt; at knowing what to show you to keep you scrolling and/or watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am not writing this to denounce the creators of these content trough algorithms for their malice nor to try to incite rebellion against them.
I am writing this to acknowledge the following fact: &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;I am very susceptible to suggested content algorithms or sources of nigh-infinite media, and to live what I feel would be a more meaningful life, I&amp;#39;m choosing to limit my exposure to them.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While these content troughs are available on both my desktop computer as well as my phone, I find myself generally more resistant on the computer.
Regardless, during times when I am trying to be productive or otherwise ensure I spend my time wisely, I have an extension in my browser that allows me to arbitrarily block and unblock sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since I consider the phone to be the contributing factor of my poorly spent time, I will focus on that for the remainder of this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-8&#34;&gt;
So what am I going to do about this phone problem?
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-8&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As romantic as the idea of reflecting on my values prior to getting distracted on my phone sounds, I know that whipping out my phone and getting sucked into the content within is a habit that must be broken.
Currently, the allure and convenience of the phone is too strong. Breaking the habit and making pulling out my phone feel more foreign (similar to how ex-smokers find holding a cigarette to be an odd feeling) will make it easier for me to be more intentional with how I choose to spend those moments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-9&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-9&#34;&gt;
1. Phone Stays Out of Reach While At Home
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-9&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest issue of the phone feels like the convenience - it&amp;#39;s in my pocket and thus available at a moment&amp;#39;s notice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thus my first action is to keep the phone on its charging pad in the bedroom while I&amp;#39;m at home instead of keeping it in my pocket or next to me on my desk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I do not regularly hang out in or pass through the bedroom during the day unless I&amp;#39;m doing chores; this location should be inconveient enough to prevent me from absent mindedly retrieving it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-10&#34; class=&#34;outline-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;headline-10&#34;&gt;
2. Aggressive Content Trough Restrictions
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-10&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I want a moment of reflection prior to being able to access a content trough where I can briefly stop myself to ask, &amp;#34;Is this what I want to do right at this moment?&amp;#34;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
To achieve this pre-content moment, I am implementing an aggressive usage of Screen Time: an explicit app allow-list via Screen Time, and web content restrictions on sites I absent mindedly access in the browser rather than via an app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the curious, here&amp;#39;s how I achieved this (note for extra clarity: iOS specific):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Settings -&amp;gt; Screen Time -&amp;gt; Downtime &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Enabled&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Every Day; From 12:00AM; To 11:59PM;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Settings -&amp;gt; Screen Time -&amp;gt; Always Allowed -&amp;gt; &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Add all apps you believe should not be restricted.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apps I kept Never Allowed: &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;comiXology, Discord, Instagram, Pokemon Go, Twitch, Twitter, YouTube&lt;/code&gt;. In this process I also deleted the &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/code&gt; app after struggling to find a reason I would need them on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the explicit allow list must be updated whenever you add a new application; this is a fairly uncommon occurence for me, so find the pros outweigh the cons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Settings -&amp;gt; Screen Time -&amp;gt; Content &amp;amp; Privacy Restrictions &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Enabled&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt; Content Restrictions -&amp;gt; Web Content -&amp;gt; &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Limit Adult Websites&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt; Never Allow -&amp;gt; &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Add all sites you want to restrict on your phone.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I only ended up restricting &lt;code class=&#34;verbatim&#34;&gt;Reddit&lt;/code&gt;, as this is effectively the only site I will absent mindedly go to and start scrolling on.
However, according to Screen Time this is the content trough where I am overwhelmingly spending excess time (up to 3 hours a day).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the other Screen Time settings, it is very difficult to allow one-time access.
If you click the &amp;#34;Allow Website&amp;#34; button when visiting a blocked page, it removes it from the &amp;#34;Never Allow&amp;#34; list and places it on the &amp;#34;Always Allow&amp;#34; list.
Thus I recommend only adding sites that you &lt;span style=&#34;text-decoration: underline;&#34;&gt;never&lt;/span&gt; want to visit on your mobile browser to this list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might ask at this point why I did not just delete the content trough apps rather than restricting them?
The reason is that I don&amp;#39;t want to make these apps completely inaccessible - each has their time and place, and I value the content and enjoyment they can bring to my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My main goal is truly to afford myself a moment of reflecting to choose to do something different if I so desire.
The content troughs are just so damn convenient, I just need to make them a little less in order to make the correct decision more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-container-headline-11&#34; class=&#34;outline-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;headline-11&#34;&gt;
In Summary
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;outline-text-headline-11&#34; class=&#34;outline-text-2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post details actions that are in process - I am still determining if the described settings enact the change in my life I desire with regards to reducing my phone usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Assuming all goes well, I will write a follow up of how reducing my phone usage and focusing on pursuits that align with my values have improved my mental health and quality of life.
One might summarize this as living a more meaningful and intentional life, which is something that I certainly want to strive to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Thank you for reading my self-improvement stream of consciousness, I hope that my internal reflecting might inspire you to do the same, or to re-evaluate how you interact with your phone. &amp;lt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
